Guide to the Delta Tau Delta records, 1890-2001
Delta Tau Delta records, 1890-2001
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Delta Tau Delta records, 1890-2002
37-4-1002
Delta Tau Delta. Beta Omicron Chapter (Cornell University).
2.1 cubic ft.
Correspondence, plans, pamphlets, printed material, the original charter of the fraternity, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, plans, pamphlets and other printed material; also, the original charter of the fraternity. Major correspondents are Malcolm J. Freeborn '29, and Edward J. Trethaway '49. Includes photographs of the various houses.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Beta Omicron Chapter of Delta Tau Delta was incorporated on January 25, 1890 at Cornell University. Original house was the old Ezra Cornell home (Forest Park).
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Since the Delta Tau Delta records came from several sources, the collection was arranged into two chronological series: the undergraduate chapter, Beta Omicron, and the alumni chapter which organized as the House Corporation and functioned with trustees. Both chapters dealt extensively with the national (arch) chapter. The primary collectors were Malcolm J. Freeborn '29 and Edward J. Trethaway '49.
The bulk of the records were created during the 1960's when there was much discussion of the role of fraternities on the campus, changing social patterns, race relations and civil rights. The collection documents the fraternity's role in pressing Cornell to develop a small group housing policy including resident advisors and the efforts of the alumni chapter to raise money for and to build a new shelter. The correspondence with the membership during the final months of the campaign (primarily the spring and summer of 1964) is arranged alphabetically to show the response of individuals to the effort. Samples were kept of the actual pledge cards and of their gathering and transmission to the University. There is a file of "The Cordelt," and there are copies of Donald L. Mallory '17, "80 Years at Cornell, 1890-1970. A History of Delta Tau Delta Fraternity at Cornell University."
Besides Freeborn and Trethaway, major correspondents are: Joseph S. Barr '18, John C. Dorfman '48, William R. Ebersol '45, Louis C. (Whitey) Edgar '33, Robert A. Eyerman '32, George B. Marchev '43, Reed L. McJunkin '32, Warner D. Orvis '06, V. Stewart Underwood '43, officers of the national chapter including: Alfred P. Sheriff and Frederick D. Kershner and officers of Cornell University including: Walter Bruska, John E. Burton, Deane W. Malott, Albert S. Miles, Neal Stamp, John Summerskill, Charles E. Warwick and J. L. Zwingle.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Delta Tau Delta.; Freeborn, Malcolm J.; Trethaway, Edward J. (Edward Joseph), 1926-; Cornell University--Societies, etc.
Subjects:
Greek letter societies.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Building plans are restricted to permission of the office of Planning Design and Construction.
RELATED MATERIAL
Edward J. Trethaway Papers, #41-5-2617. Divison of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Beta Omicron Chapter (undergraduate)
Box 1
Series II. House Corporation (alumni)
Boxes 2-6
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Beta Omicron Chapter (undergraduate)
  - Activities: Rushing, reunion, summer jobs, etc. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Activities: Peter Schneck's shelter design project, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial reports, 1957-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Shelter operations, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Shelter operations, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chapter advisor, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chapter advisor, Mr. Freeborn's notes, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Cordelt," 1926-1977, miscellaneous issues (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Cordelt," 1978-2001 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Membership directories: 1932, 1950, 1957, 1963, 1969, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous publications including: Donald L. Mallory '17, "80 Years at Cornell, 1890-1970. A History of Delta Tau Delta Fraternity at Cornell University." (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Relations with the Arch Chapter (National Office), Secret matter (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Statistics, 1930-1957 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Form letters, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Form letters, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Form letters, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Form letters, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Form letters, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Relations with the Eastern Division, Form letters, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photographs, Delta Tau Delta brothers, 1946, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 1, 2)
  - Photographs, Formal parties and Spring Day group shots, 1947, 1948, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 2, 3)
  - Original charter (Folder 1)
  - Photographs of house (Folder 1)
- Series II. House Corporation (alumni)
  - Governing documents
    - Certificate of Incorporation [photostat], June 7, 1890, approved and filed June 16, 1890. Constitution and By-Laws, 1905, 1911, 1920, n.d., n.d., 1963, 1964. Correspondence relative to ammendments. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - National Constitution and By-Laws. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Officers and trustees, 1946-1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Agenda and minutes of meetings, 1954-1959. Occassionally minutes of other groups and sometimes correspondence and documents are attached. See 1957 for a housing proposal, for example. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Agenda and minutes of meetings, 1960-1964. See 10/22/60 for Warner Orvis' financial history of the local chapter. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Agenda and minutes of meetings, 1965-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Our Future Image at Beta Omicron Chapter of Delta Tau Delta Fraternity," by Malcolm J. Freeborn, June 19, 1965. The publication of a speech delivered upon his resignation as president of the House Corporation. Correspondence included. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1968, visit of Justice Tom C. Clark (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1969, Trethaway's "Statement...," 10/11/69 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1996-1998, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Stewart Howe Alumni Service, Correspondence, 1957-1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Stewart Howe Alumni Service, Position papers (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cornell University, Group Housing
    - Group housing, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Group housing, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Group housing, January-August, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Group housing, August-December, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Group housing, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Group housing, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Group housing, 1966-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Commission on Residential Environment" [Saperston Commission], 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Cornell Intrafraternity Alumni Association/Resident Fraternity Advisors, 1958-1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Resident Advisor Program, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Clippings and Statistics relating to fraternities, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - New Shelter, Fundraising Committee"
    - Organization, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Form letters, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Information, 1961; "Solicitor Instructions," "Donor Information," "Finance Committee Report, New Chapter House" (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Lists and reports, 1924-1961 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Lists and reports, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Lists and reports, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lists and reports, 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence with members, A (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with members, B (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with members, C (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with members, D (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence with members, E (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with members, F (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence with members, G (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with members, H (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence with members, J (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with members, K (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence with members, L (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence with members, M (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence with members, Mason (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence with members, N (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence with members, O (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence with members, P-Q (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence with members, R (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence with members, S (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence with members T (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence with members, Tinan (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence with members, V (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence with members, W (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence with members, Warner (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence with members, Y (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - New Shelter, Building Committee
    - Building Committee (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Robert A. Eyerman '32 F.A.I.A., 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Robert A. Eyerman '32 F.A.I.A., 1964 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Robert A. Eyerman '32 F.A.I.A. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Specifications, "Group House Number Seven," February 18, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Specifications (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Dedication, Correspondence, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Dedication, Programs and speeches (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Dedication, "Forest Park," by Professor Stephen W. Jacobs (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Dedication, Publications and photographs (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - RESTRICTED: Whiteprints, May 2, 1963, "F" July 9, 1963, "G" August 1, 1963, "I" October 23, 1963, "No.12" February 18, 1965 [24 p.] (Map-case Folder 1)
    - RESTRICTED: Whiteprints, September 13, 1963, "H" [4 p.] (Map-case Folder 1)
  - Old Shelter
    - Old shelter, 110 Edgemoor Lane, Appraisal, Warren Real Estate, May 6, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Sale to Cornell, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Second Century Fund, Centennial, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - "Appraisal of the Delta Tau Delta House..., May 18, 1912;" The American Appraisal Company, Milwaukee, Wisconsin. Includes a full description of the building and all furnishings. Bound volume, 91 pages plus measured drawings. (Box 6)
    - Plaque, "In Memory of Willard D. Straight '01, Donated by Joseph D. Trethaway '19 and Edward J. Trethaway '49" (Box 6)
    - Forest Park, 10 photographs, 11"x13" (Home of Ezra Cornell and his descendants, 1957 to 1929 and site of new shelter). (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Old house/new house memento with correspondence, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Photograph, 1947, of Otto, Prager[?], Orvis, and Wigton (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Printed copy of photograph of Delta Tau Delta, 1896-1965, at 110 Edgemoor Lane, bought by Cornell 1965 and torn down (Box 8)
    - Photographs of Delta Tau Delta house, 110 Edgemoor Lane, interior and exterior (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Negatives of Delta Tau Delta house, 110 Edgemoor Lane, interior and exterior (Box 8, Folder 5)